Finding Aid for J. Edgar Edwards Papers 1938-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
J. Edgar Edwards Papers 1938-1973
Edwards, J. Edgar (Joseph Edgar), 1909-1973.
5 linear feet
Minister and director of the Guild House, Ann Arbor, Michigan, religious cooperative. Sermons, prayers, addresses, poetry, course notes from Union Theological Seminary, and marriage ceremonies; also papers concerning the 1965 and 1967 teach-ins at the University of Michigan on the war in Vietnam, draft counseling, conscientious objection, Students for a Democratic Society and other political groups, and miscellanea.
85142 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Alice E. Edwards (donor no. 4537 ) in 1977.
The collection is open for research.
J. Edgar Edwards received his Bachelor of Divinity from Union Theological Seminary in 1942 and began his career at the First Congregational Christian Church in Maplewood, New Jersey. Leaving in 1946, he became director of the Willow Run Village Church Fellowship Council. In 1950 he became rector of St. Paul's Episcopal Church in Hillsdale, Michigan. From 1951 to 1954 Edwards lived in Dedham, Mass and worked in Boston for the Student Christian Movement, visiting many colleges and universities in New England. In 1954 he accepted the pastorate of Edwards' Memorial Congregational Church in Edwardsville, Pennsylvania. Edwards came to Ann Arbor as director and campus minister of the Guild House in 1957 and remained until his death in 1973.
The collection contains sermons (1941-1973) which deal primarily with the church's and the individual's role in society. Also included are Edward's class notes and papers from the Union Theological Seminary, lecture notes for the various courses on non-violence and other subjects which Edwards taught, and marriage programs including the vows written by individual couples. The papers include pamphlets, newsletters, notebooks, and clippings designed to assist in counseling conscientious objectors. Edwards participated in the Vietnam War teach-ins of 1965 and 1967, addressing the meetings both times. Material of the Students for a Democratic Society and other radical political groups are included.
Subjects:
Clergy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Conscientious objectors.; Edwards, J. Edgar (Joseph Edgar), 1909-1973.; Guild House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); International Conference on Alternative Perspectives on Vietnam (1965: University of Michigan); Michigan--Social life and customs--20th century.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; Peace--Societies, etc.; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.); Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.); University of Michigan--Religion.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975.
- Correspondence
  - 1938-1942, 1951, 1968-1973 (Box 1)
- Newspaper clippings
  - 1958-1965, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Sermons and related
  - Undated, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Fragments (Box 1)
  - 1940-1951, 21 folders (Box 1)
  - 1952-1973, 21 folders (Box 2)
  - Prayers 1956-1968 (Box 2)
  - "Statement of Christian faith and purpose and some theological attitudes centering upon Current Concerns," 1955 (Box 2)
  - Addresses undated, 1948-1968, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Poetry undated, 1968-1973 (Box 2)
  - Radio broadcasts 1942-1956 (Box 2)
- Course notes and syllabi
  - Union Theological Seminary courses
    - Miscellaneous and undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Christian ethics 1938 (Box 2)
    - Christian ethics 1940-1941 (Box 2)
    - Christian ethics "Propaganda agencies in America for and against intervention in European war," 1941 (Box 2)
    - Christian institutions, Congregationalism 1940 (Box 3)
    - Christian leadership 1938-1939 (Box 3)
    - Christian leadership 1940 (Box 3)
    - Church and community undated (Box 3)
    - Church history undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Church history 1940-1941 (Box 3)
    - Church history paper, "Wyclif and Lombardy: early seeds of English non-conformity, an attempt to trace its effects, " 1941 (Box 3)
    - Church history 1942 (Box 3)
    - Comparative study of religions 1942
      - Buddhism (Box 3)
      - Confucianism (Box 3)
      - Hinduism (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous religions (Box 3)
    - Counseling 1940-1942 (Box 3)
    - Democratic process 1940-1941 (Box 3)
    - General examination 1941 (Box 3)
    - History of Christian thought undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Missions 1942 (Box 3)
    - New Testament undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - New Testament paper, "'Grace' in the Gospel of Luke and Acts of the Apostles," undated (Box 3)
    - New Testament 1939-1940 (Box 3)
    - New Testament 1941-1942 (Box 3)
    - New Testament paper, "The operation of the Spirit," 1942 (Box 3)
    - Old Testament 1938 (Box 3)
    - Old Testament 1940 (Box 3)
    - Philosophy of religion 1938-1939 (Box 3)
    - Philosophy of religion readings 1940-1941, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Philosophy of religion 1940-1941, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Philosophy of religion paper, "The Oxford Group Movement," 1941 (Box 3)
    - Practical theology 1938 (Box 3)
    - Practical theology 1942 (Box 3)
    - Religious education undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Systematic theology undated (Box 3)
    - Systematic theology 1940 (Box 3)
    - Systematic theology 1941 (Box 3)
    - Systematic theology 1942 (Box 3)
    - "A systematic Theology (Paul Tillich)," 1942 (Box 3)
  - Related materials
    - "Development of property and class in the Hebrew society, "1938 (Box 4)
    - Bachelor of Divinity thesis. "The integration of worship with other aspects of the Church's program" 1942 (Box 4)
    - Post-exile prophets (course taken by Alice Edwards) 1940 (Box 4)
- Various notes, conference material, etc.
  - Course notes (Jewish Theological Seminary of America) 1945-1946 (Box 4)
  - Michigan pastor's conference 1950 (Box 4)
  - Conference on the urban church, Pawling, New York 1954 (Box 4)
  - Lecture notes
    - Miscellanea (Box 4)
    - Religious journals study group 1959 (Box 4)
    - Newman undated (Box 4)
    - Christian belief undated (Box 4)
    - Christian faith 1955 undated, 1960 (Box 4)
    - History of Christian thought 1962-1966 (Box 4)
    - Lenten Bible study 1969 (Box 4)
  - Student papers: History and philosophy of non-violence 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Bibliographies and syllabi of classes taught (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous writings of others (Box 4)
  - Marriage ceremony programs 1962-1973, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Defense of performing non-traditional marriage ceremonies undated (Box 4)
  - Radical College 1967-1970 (Box 4)
- Draft Counseling and Related
  - Central Committee for Conscientious Objectors
    - Miscellaneous papers 1967-1969 (Box 4)
    - Draft counseling memos 1970-1972 (Box 4)
    - Draft Counselor's Newsletter 1970 (Box 4)
    - Draft Counselor's Newsletter 1971 (Box 4)
    - Draft Counselor's Newsletter 1972-1973 (Box 4)
    - News Notes 1967-1973 (Box 4)
    - Newsletter on Military Law and Counseling 1973 (Box 4)
  - Michigan draft information exchange 1970-1972 (Box 4)
  - American Friends service committee 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous draft counseling materials 1969-1971 (Box 4)
  - "Confrontation with the draft: The development of values and self-identity (Paul Hillegonds)," 1967 (Box 4)
  - Draft Counseling pamphlets 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - Draft resistance clippings 1965, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Draft counseling notebooks 1967, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Student legal defense committee (list of contributors) undated (Box 4)
- Vietnam peace movement
  - National teach-in press kit 1965 (Box 5)
  - Teach-in addresses by Edwards 1965, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Teach-in clippings 1965 (Box 5)
  - Teach-in miscellanea 1965 (Box 5)
  - Elise Boulding Congressional write-in campaign 1966 (Box 5)
  - Miscellanea undated, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Viet Reports 1965-1968 (Box 5)
  - Vietnam miscellaneous printed materials 1965-1968 (Box 5)
  - Vietnam dialogue bibliography 1966 (Box 5)
- Other Issues
  - Ann Arbor Committee for Sane Nuclear Policy 1959-1960 (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor Citizens for New Politics 1967 (Box 5)
  - Students for a Democratic Society 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - Student government election 1960 (Box 5)
  - Student government power struggle 1966 (Box 5)
  - Black power 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - "We walked to Moscow," by Jerry Lehmann 1966 (Box 5)
  - "You come with naked hands: The story of the San Francisco to Moscow march for peace," by Bradford Lyttle 1966 (Box 5)
  - North American Congress on Latin America 1968 (Box 5)
  - Speech by Fidel Castro (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous printed works, 5 folders (Box 5)